so we're going to find that there's a
number of different ways that we can
read through the file but the most
common way that we're going to read
through the file is to treat it as a
sequence of lines and we're going to use
the determinant Loop the four Loop uh to
do this and so what happens here is we
get back this handle that opens the file
and gives us back the handle that handle
x file is the variable I named call I
just named it x file that's not the data
but it is a sequence it is that file
handle represents to python a sequence
that we can potentially walk through and
then get all the lines and it's the
simplest most beautiful elegant way to
read all the lines in a file we use the
for Loop and we have an iteration
variable this is going to take when we
talk about the file cheese is going to
be the first line then the second line
then the third line then the fourth line
so it's it's like going through a string
but you're going through a file now and
you're getting it line by line so that's
each line I just picked a variable named
cheese so you didn't get confused later
I'll call this line but it but python
doesn't know anything special by naming
that variable line okay and so this is
It's the four and the n and so so for I
read this as for each line in the file X
the file handle x file so run this Loop
one time for every line and then print
it out so it's actually really quite
simple okay um other languages like C or
C++ or other languages they have to
write while loops with end of file
conditions and all kinds of things that
make this very difficult but this is one
of the prettiest things that uh python
has it's a it's a very very pretty
thing okay so let's talk about what we
might do and we're going kind of back to
iterations now what if we wanted to
count the number of lines in a file well
this is a basic Loop counting pattern so
we open the file and then like in all
these Loops we do something to sort of
prime the loop to get it started set a
variable count to zero and I'm going to
use the variable line that's going to go
through each of line lines in the file
for line in fand down the file and it's
going to run this Loop once for each
line in the file and the variable line
is going to change but all I'm going to
do is add count equals count plus one
and so that's just like from counters
that's just how you detect so every time
we see a line we're just going to add
one to the counter we're not printing
the line we're not even looking at its
data at this point and then when the
line is done however many times it has
to go out it comes and we print out line
count equals count and so if we open
inbox. txt this is going to do all this
work and then print this line out and
say line count is
132,000 45 so this is a little feline
program that shows you how to count the
lines in a text file using python again
simple and elegant and not too much
synex for you to have to
learn now it's also possible to read the
file as a series of characters all in
one go read the whole file in now you
got to be careful depending on the size
of the file this is going to lead to a
string variable ible with a lot of data
in it now if it's you know 100,000
characters that's actually kind of a
small thing but if it was uh you know 10
million lines that would probably not be
good you'd want to read it one line at a
time and process each line and then do
something but Mbox short. txt is a small
little file so we open it and we get
back a file object file handle object
and we call the read method and that
says go through and read all the text
and give it back in one Big Blob one big
string and I'll put it in imp and so
that's where you have a line a new line
a line a new line a line a new line it's
not really lines it's just a sequence of
characters with new lines in there to
punctuate them and now you can split
that later we'll see how to split that
um into uh separate lines if you want
now I picked a file that was short and
so this in variable now has a string in
it and I can use the Len function pass a
string into the Len function it says oh
9462 six characters that's kind of a
small um a small little file and
perfectly okay to read it all in one go
and so now I say just print the first 20
characters that's you know beginning to
up to but not including 20 and so it
shows the the first TW 20 characters of
that little file is a from line because
this is a mailbox
file now let's say we're going to do a
searching and we did this Loop where
you're looking for something and so
we're going to search for lines that
have a prefix of
from okay that's what we're going to do
and we're going to print those lines out
so there's lots of lines in this
file you know line line line line from
line line line line from right on and on
and on and we don't we only want to show
these lines the ones that match right
that's what we want to do and
so we are going to write an open
statement and then we're going to Loop
through and we're going to ask the
question if the line starts with from
print it so sometimes it's going to
going to skip skip skip skip and then
it's going to run it then Skip Skip Skip
Skip Skip it's going to run it Skip Skip
Skip and then it's going to run it okay
so that's the basic idea and then then
it'll finish when it's all said and done
and so this is like an a criteria this
is like a search we're looking for lines
that match the string that have the
string from as their
prefix now when we look at the output of
this it's kind of weird we see kind of
these little blank lines that show blank
blank blank blank blank blank blank
what's going on here what's going on so
let's take a quick
look the problem is is new lines well I
mentioned that the file has new lines in
them and so when you do the for Loop it
doesn't throw the new lines away as you
might expect it would be kind of nice if
it did but it doesn't it actually shows
you when it when you read it reads that
first line up to and including the new
line and gives you that back as the the
variable so that is the First new line
so that means it's going to go down and
then the print statement actually adds
another new line so that's the the
second line of the file has a new line
at the end of it and the print statement
adds another new line so if we take a
look at the
code there is a new line oops come
back if we take a look at the code this
variable line has a new line in it oops
where am I at I'm in the wrong slide
there we
go
yeah this the one I want to do if we
look at the code there's a new line in
here and then the print adds another new
line so the print adds a separate new
line and that's how we get two new lines
the print statements new line and the
new line from the
file here's how we fix it and you're
going to write this code a lot because
when you're reading text files you end
up with a new line and often you don't
want the new line but
thankfully as we saw in the previous
chapter there is a nice little function
in uh python for string
called strip that allows you to throw
away whites
space and to
review remember Whit space is anything
that doesn't print and this new line is
not a non-printing character so our
strip gets rid of it so it's a way to
get rid of whites space and R strip does
it from the right end so it's the right
end of the F of the of the
string and so if we just are going to
Loop through all the lines in the file
we say line equals line rstrip and then
this variable no longer has the new line
at the end of it we have our little if
statement and if we print it then this
line the data has no thing and then the
print the data has a no new line in it
so the print only goes down one and so
now we have single spaced output and so
you're going to be doing that a lot it's
really common to read through a file and
then just strip the new line or any
trailing space off the end of that now
there's a couple of ways to do a loop
like this and let's let's just think of
this says um we're looking for a a line
a file with lots of different lines in
it and we want to ignore all the lines
except some say good lines and we want
to do something with those good lines or
the lines we're looking for needle in a
Hy stack this is like searching for a
needle in the Hy stack so if you look at
this code at high level we're going to
Loop through everything and then we're
sort of picking which lines are and
these are the good lines down here now
often we have a bunch more code that we
want to do and we're not just printing
them but we're going to do a lot of code
so some times you actually structure the
loop a little bit differently and so the
way to do it and this is going to do the
exact same thing it's just a little
different way of thinking about this
Loop so the top part is the same we're
stripping it and what we're doing here
is it it's everything's the same here
except we add this in not if the line
does not start with from that's the
translation of that if the line does not
start with from continue so basically we
have a skipping pattern so the lines
we're not interested in we skip so we
come down we you know Skip a lot of
lines and then we find a line that's
good and then we fall through so this is
the good code and then we have all the
other good code that we want to do to
that line we have that showing up down
here um and so there's just two patterns
that two ways to do the exact same thing
so another way to select the lines that
we're interested in is to use the in
operator so we talked before about the
in operator and how that works so we're
basically and I'm going to use the
continue skipping method so we're going
to read all the lines these first few
lines if u. ac. Za is not in the line
skip it and so this is going to print
out all the lines that have the string
UCT a Za in them in them and so you see
this is the output of the program dot
dot dot dot
dot sometimes you'll have programs that
want to read different files often I
give assignments where I say show me how
this program runs on the short file and
then show me again how it runs on the
long file just like this and so the way
we do that to input the file name
instead of making the file name be a
constant to the open call we make the
file name be a input so we just run an
input statement which gives us a prompt
and then we type inbox. txt and then
that shows up in this variable F name
it's a course of string all the time and
we pass that into open and then we open
it and then we do you know the count
operation so if we enter inbox. txt it
counts 179 7
1797 um subject lines in Mbox and if we
give it Mbox short it says there are 27
subject lines in Mbox and again this is
another one of those ifs and it's just
counting but only counting lines that
match a particular uh a particular
uh
pattern okay so now the user can also
type bad file names and we need to be
able to deal with that as well and so we
we're we're taking a small small change
to the code the danger the dangerous
code is this line right here this line
right here is going to trace back if
that file doesn't exist so what do we do
well we're going to just expand that the
rest of this program is exactly the same
the only thing's different is we we've
got this line we took out insurance on
it and we know that it might blow up and
so we we have it in a try and accept
block so here's how the code
runs so you know the input runs we type
in a good file name comes in here this
works and so it skips the accept and so
it runs the code and prints out the
count so that's the good pattern the bad
pattern
is here we type in a bad file name it
comes in the tri accept this file name
is naab Boo Boo and it's going to blow
up so this line blows up so it jumps
down into the accept code prints out
file cannot be open so prints this out
now this quit is really important
because if we don't put this quit in
here it's going to continue down here
and that's going to blow up here CU file
handle is not defined properly at this
point and so what we have is we have
this quit op quit is a special function
where it comes in and never returns so
this is a way to terminate the entire
Python program silently with no Trace
back right so we put in our own error
message so we look like we're
professional say could not open this
file and then we stop if you don't it's
going to come down here and it's going
to trace back Trace back right there
going to blow up so um the quit is
useful when you want to stop executing
because you've detected some kind of an
error so that's a quick Zoom through
opening and reading through files and uh
doing some patterns
um most of the rest of the programs in
this course are going to say open for R
strip do look for and then do something
interesting that's going to be our Loop
that we're going to do over and over and
over again and now we see how this
looping and if and iteration and
variables are are starting to come
together and you can actually sort of do
a program that does something useful but
before we get to too many more programs
we got to switch a little bit switch
gears and talk up next about data
structures and that is the shape of data
um and how we can use more intricate and
complex variables to help solve our
problems